<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speciesPage><NAME_CD>FRPE</NAME_CD><group>PLANT</group><desc><growthForm>DUMMYDATA</growthForm><size>Medium-sized tree, 12 - 18 m tall, trunk diameter 30 cm - 0.6 m. Trunk straight, stout, sometimes slightly expanded at the base. Crown dense, rounded to irregular.</size><parts><part><partName>Bark</partName><partText>brown or dark gray, thick, furrowed into scaly, interlacing ridges.</partText></part><part><partName>Twigs</partName><partText>stout, ashy gray to reddish brown; current shoots may be densely hairy at first (persisting 1 - 3 years). Leaf scars are half-circles with a flat top, with several bundle scars forming a U. Epidermis of older, hairless twigs not peeling or flaking.</partText></part><part><partName>Buds</partName><partText>dark brown, small, rounded, finely hairy. Terminal bud 3 - 8 mm long. Uppermost pair of lateral buds adjacent to terminal bud at nearly the same level.</partText></part><part><partName>Leaves</partName><partText>opposite, pinnately compound, with smooth (sometimes hairy) leafstalks; 25 - 30 cm long, with 7 - 9 leaflets. Leaflets short-stalked, yellowish green, 7 - 15 cm long, 2.5 - 4.5 cm wide, oblong lance-shaped to egg-shaped, tapering at the base, long-pointed at the tip, margins slightly toothed, thin, firm, hairy on both surfaces. Leaves turn yellowish brown in autumn.</partText></part><part><partName>Flowers</partName><partText>either male or female, found on separate trees (dioecious); borne in a downy, branched inflorescence; purplish or greenish, tiny; calyx cup-shaped.</partText></part><part><partName>Fruit</partName><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText>dry, single-seeded, winged (samara); in open, branched clusters; 2.5 - 5 cm long, narrow-cylindrical; wing enclosing half or more of seed cavity.</partText></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part></parts></desc><similarSpecies><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt; is best identified by having short-stalked leaflets, densely hairy current shoots (some trees), and fruit with a wing enclosing half or more of the seed cavity. The epidermis of older, hairless twigs does not peel or flake. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus americana&lt;/i&gt; has pale or whitish undersides, twigs with raised leaf scars, fruit with large seed cavities having a wing which doesn’t extend to the base, and a flaky, scaly, or peeling twig epidermis (except current year’s growth). &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus nigra&lt;/i&gt; has unstalked leaflets, and fruit with a wing extending near the base of the flat seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus profunda&lt;/i&gt; has longer, wider, more leathery leaflets, densely hairy shoots (current), and fruit with a wing often extending to the base of the seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus quadrangulata&lt;/i&gt; has square twigs, and fruit with a wing extending to and around the base of the seed cavity.</comments><nameCds><simNmCd>FRAM2</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRNI</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRPR</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRQU</simNmCd><simNmCd/><simNmCd/></nameCds><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></similarSpecies><flowering>April to mid-May, after the leaves have begun to open.</flowering><habitatEcology>Frequent in woods, usually not far from water.</habitatEcology><nativity>native</nativity><notes><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt; is the most widely distributed native ash in North America. It has both hairless (called green ash) and hairy (red ash) forms, observable on twigs, leaf parts, and flower and fruit branchings. The hairless form, green ash, is often planted as an ornamental. The wood of &lt;i&gt;F. pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt; is used for tool handles, interior finishing, furniture, oars, paddles, tennis rackets, and baseball bats. The emerald ash borer (&lt;i&gt;Agrilus planipennis&lt;/i&gt;) is a serious insect threat to all native ashes (see link below).</comments><links><link><linkUri>Emerald Ash Borer</linkUri><linkText>http://www.emeraldashborer.info/</linkText></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></notes><etymology><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus&lt;/i&gt; is the Latin word for ash. &lt;i&gt;Pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt; means “of or from Pennsylvania.”</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></etymology><furtherInfo><comments/><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></furtherInfo><references><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference></references><otherRecords><ilBn>has other records</ilBn><ilCk>has other records</ilCk><ilDk>has other records</ilDk><ilDp>has other records</ilDp><ilGd>has other records</ilGd><ilKd>has other records</ilKd><ilKk/><ilKn>has other records</ilKn><ilLk>has other records</ilLk><ilMh>has other records</ilMh><ilWl>has other records</ilWl><inJs>has other records</inJs><inLk>has other records</inLk><inLp>has other records</inLp><inNt>has other records</inNt><inPt>has other records</inPt><inSj/><inSk>has other records</inSk><miBr>has other records</miBr><wiKs/><wiMw>has other records</wiMw><wiRc>has other records</wiRc><wiWk/><wiWw>has other records</wiWw></otherRecords></speciesPage>