<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speciesPage><NAME_CD>PISY</NAME_CD><group>PLANT</group><desc><growthForm>DUMMYDATA</growthForm><size>Tree, 15 - 30 m tall, trunk diameter to 0.5 m; variable. Crown pyramidal to rounded and irregular.</size><parts><part><partName>Bark</partName><partText>pale gray, thin, with scaly ridges on young trees. Older trees grayish brown, thicker, fissured into scaly plates, peeling, becoming distinctly orange-brown in the mid and upper trunk.</partText></part><part><partName>Twigs</partName><partText>slender, reddish to orange-brown, becoming grayish brown and rough with age.</partText></part><part><partName>Buds</partName><partText>reddish brown, about 6 mm long, cylindrical to egg-shaped, pointed.</partText></part><part><partName>Needles</partName><partText>in clusters of two, waxy bluish green, 4 - 6 cm long, twisted, sharp-pointed, rigid, thick, somewhat flattened.</partText></part><part><partName>Pollen cones</partName><partText>yellow or pale pink, about 6 mm long, egg-shaped, clustered at the base of new shoots.</partText></part><part><partName>Young seed cones</partName><partText>Mature seed cones</partText></part><part><partName>woody, short-stalked, hanging downward, dull gray to yellowish brown, 3 - 8 cm long, egg-shaped to somewhat spherical; scales thin and flattened, thickening at the apex into a 4-sided point without a prickle, resembling a miniature volcano. Seeds grayish to reddish brown, 3 - 6 mm long, with wings up to 15 mm long.</partName><partText>purple, about 6 mm long, egg-shaped, at the tips of new shoots in upper crown. Pollination between cones occurs mid to late May.</partText></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part></parts></desc><similarSpecies><comments>&lt;i&gt;Pinus sylvestris&lt;/i&gt; is best identified by its distinct orange-brown bark in the mid and upper trunk, its short, bluish green needles in clusters of two, and its egg-shaped seed cones with scales that thicken at the apex into a 4-sided, unarmed point, resembling a miniature volcano. &lt;i&gt;Pinus banksiana&lt;/i&gt; has yellowish green needles, curved, unarmed seed cones, and a generally scrubby appearance. &lt;i&gt;Pinus pungens&lt;/i&gt; has slightly longer (5 - 10 cm), bluish green needles and heavy, egg-shaped seed cones with thick, prickled scales. &lt;i&gt;Pinus virginiana&lt;/i&gt; has soft, flexible, dark green needles and reddish brown, egg-shaped seed cones armed with a long prickle.</comments><nameCds><simNmCd>PIBA2</simNmCd><simNmCd>PIPU5</simNmCd><simNmCd>PIVI2</simNmCd><simNmCd/><simNmCd/><simNmCd/></nameCds><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></similarSpecies><flowering/><habitatEcology>Grows on just about any upland soil when planted, and flourishes on sandy loam soils. It has reproduced and naturalized well at Illinois Beach State Park south of Zion in Lake County, Illinois. Spontaneous plants also occur elsewhere in the Chicago Region, particularly near old plantings.</habitatEcology><nativity>non-native</nativity><notes><comments>Introduced from Europe. &lt;i&gt;Pinus sylvestris&lt;/i&gt; is one of the most widely distributed pines in the world, with many races and varieties recognized. It’s an attractive tree, often planted around buildings or homes, and is grown in plantations for Christmas trees. Some races of &lt;i&gt;P. sylvestris&lt;/i&gt; are susceptible to the European pine shoot moth (&lt;i&gt;Rhyacionia buolina&lt;/i&gt;), the pine wilt fungus, and Diplodia needle-cast disease, thereby rendering them undesirable in landscapes. The wood is used for general construction, pulp, posts, and boxes.</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></notes><etymology><comments>&lt;i&gt;Pinus&lt;/i&gt; is the Latin word for pine. &lt;i&gt;Strobus&lt;/i&gt; is the Latin word for pinecone.</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></etymology><furtherInfo><comments/><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></furtherInfo><references><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference></references><otherRecords><ilBn/><ilCk/><ilDk/><ilDp>has other records</ilDp><ilGd/><ilKd>has other records</ilKd><ilKk/><ilKn/><ilLk>has other records</ilLk><ilMh/><ilWl/><inJs/><inLk/><inLp>has other records</inLp><inNt/><inPt>has other records</inPt><inSj/><inSk/><miBr/><wiKs/><wiMw/><wiRc/><wiWk/><wiWw/></otherRecords></speciesPage>