<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speciesPage><NAME_CD>ULAM</NAME_CD><group>PLANT</group><desc><growthForm>DUMMYDATA</growthForm><size>Large tree to 20 - 30 m tall, trunk diameter 0.5 - 1.2 m. Trunk commonly divided into a few large trunks, and forked into many spreading branches with drooping ends, which form a broad, rounded, flat-topped, or vase-shaped crown.</size><parts><part><partName>Bark</partName><partText>ashy gray, thick, furrowed into broad, interlacing, scaly ridges; with alternating light and dark colored bands in cross section.</partText></part><part><partName>Twigs</partName><partText>slender, firm, light green, becoming ashy gray; smooth or sparsely hairy. Leaf scars half-round, covered with a corky layer, having 3 bundle scars.</partText></part><part><partName>Buds</partName><partText>reddish brown, 3 - 6 mm long, broadly egg-shaped, blunt to pointed, flattened, smooth or slightly hairy.</partText></part><part><partName>Leaves</partName><partText>alternate, with short, stout, yellowish leafstalks; dark green and sometimes rough above, pale and usually softly hairy beneath; 10 - 15 cm long, half as wide, oval to elliptic, base asymmetrical, tip pointed, margins coarsely doubly-toothed, thick, firm, veins rarely forked. Leaves turning yellow in autumn. Note: leaf morphology is highly variable for this species.</partText></part><part><partName>Flowers</partName><partText>with both male and female reproductive organs (perfect); in loose, drooping clusters; brownish red, small, calyx bell-shaped.</partText></part><part><partName>Fruit</partName><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText>single-seeded, winged (samara); in crowded clusters; long-stalked, 1.2 cm long, oval, margin hairy, tip deeply notched.</partText></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part></parts></desc><similarSpecies><comments>&lt;i&gt;Ulmus procera&lt;/i&gt; has smaller leaves (5 - 8 cm long) and hairless samaras. &lt;i&gt;Ulmus pumila&lt;/i&gt; also has smaller leaves (3 - 7 cm long), which are not distinctly asymmetrical at the base or doubly-toothed. &lt;i&gt;Ulmus rubra&lt;/i&gt; has very rough leaves, forked veins near the leaf margin, rusty-colored bud hairs, and brown, hairy seed cavities. &lt;i&gt;Ulmus thomasii&lt;/i&gt; has corky wings on the twigs, leaves with a nearly symmetrical base, and hairy samaras. Characteristics of the hybrid &lt;i&gt;U. x notha&lt;/i&gt; are intermediate of the two parents, &lt;i&gt;U. pumila&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;U. rubra&lt;/i&gt;. The most distinctive features are the middle bud scales fringed with white hairs and the terminal scales fringed with reddish brown hairs. &lt;i&gt;Celtis&lt;/i&gt; leaves, which are similar in appearance, have three main veins arising from the base of each blade.</comments><nameCds><simNmCd>ULPR</simNmCd><simNmCd>ULPU</simNmCd><simNmCd>ULRU</simNmCd><simNmCd>ULTH</simNmCd><simNmCd>ULNO</simNmCd><simNmCd/></nameCds><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></similarSpecies><flowering>March to mid-May, before the leaves.</flowering><habitatEcology>Common in rich woods, wooded floodplains, and along streams, but can be found in a wide variety of soil types.</habitatEcology><nativity>native</nativity><notes><comments>&lt;i&gt;Ulmus americana&lt;/i&gt; is frequently planted as an ornamental and shade tree. Because of its attractive vase-shaped branching, this species was planted extensively along town and city streets by early Europeans, forming beautiful cathedral-like avenues. Since the mid-1950’s, both the street plantings and the wild populations in the Chicago Region have been severely decimated by Dutch elm disease and phloem necrosis. Today, disease-resistant clones and hybrids are available for planting. The wood of &lt;i&gt;Ulmus americana&lt;/i&gt; is used for furniture, flooring, boxes, crates, barrels, veneer, and shipbuilding. See link to Dutch elm disease below.</comments><links><link><linkUri>Dutch Elm Disease</linkUri><linkText>http://www.mortonarb.org/plantinfo/plantclinic/diseases_dutchelm.pdf</linkText></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></notes><etymology><comments>&lt;i&gt;Ulmus&lt;/i&gt; is the Latin word for elm. &lt;i&gt;Americana&lt;/i&gt; means “of or from America” (North or South).</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></etymology><furtherInfo><comments/><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></furtherInfo><references><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference></references><otherRecords><ilBn>has other records</ilBn><ilCk>has other records</ilCk><ilDk>has other records</ilDk><ilDp>has other records</ilDp><ilGd>has other records</ilGd><ilKd>has other records</ilKd><ilKk/><ilKn>has other records</ilKn><ilLk>has other records</ilLk><ilMh>has other records</ilMh><ilWl>has other records</ilWl><inJs>has other records</inJs><inLk>has other records</inLk><inLp>has other records</inLp><inNt>has other records</inNt><inPt>has other records</inPt><inSj>has other records</inSj><inSk>has other records</inSk><miBr>has other records</miBr><wiKs/><wiMw>has other records</wiMw><wiRc>has other records</wiRc><wiWk/><wiWw>has other records</wiWw></otherRecords></speciesPage>