<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speciesPage><NAME_CD>GESA</NAME_CD><group>PLANT</group><desc><growthForm>Perennial herb</growthForm><size>8 - 70 cm tall</size><parts><part><partName>Stem</partName><partText>normally unbranched, usually hairless, but sometimes with short, swollen-based hairs.</partText></part><part><partName>Leaves</partName><partText>opposite, stalkless, dark green, less than 2 cm wide, and short hairy on the margins. The leaf shape is variable, ranging from linear to elliptic, but usually widest near the middle, possibly blunt-tipped, but never long pointy.</partText></part><part><partName>Flowers</partName><partText>stalkless, blue (sometimes violet), open to loosely closed, and in clusters of one to eight at the top of the stem, but also at the end of branches at the upper part of the stem in larger individuals.  Each flower is subtended by a pair of bracts, which are longer than wide.</partText></part><part><partName>Sepals</partName><partText>five but fused at least half their length into a hairless, 5 - 15 mm long tube.  Sepal tips shorter than or about equal to the length of the tube, narrow (0.8 - 4 mm wide), with pointy tips and hairy margins.</partText></part><part><partName>Petals</partName><partText>five, lobes at the tips usually incurved, alternating with evidently jagged or two-toothed, fused membranes (plaits) about the same length as the petals. The actual petals seldom exceed the interconnected plaits by more than 2 mm.</partText></part><part><partName>Anthers</partName><partText>five but fused together.</partText></part><part><partName>Fruit</partName><partText>a two-valved, elliptic capsule with numerous flattened, winged, smooth seeds.</partText></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part></parts></desc><similarSpecies><comments>&lt;i&gt;Gentiana saponaria&lt;/i&gt; has often been confused with a more southeastern species, &lt;i&gt;G. catesbaei&lt;/i&gt;, but it has brighter green, wider leaves, which are widest near the base, not the middle.  Also in &lt;i&gt;G. catesbaei&lt;/i&gt;, the sepal tips are longer than the tube and the petal lobes are usually 2 - 4 mm longer than the alternating plaits.  &lt;i&gt;Gentiana saponaria&lt;/i&gt; is also often confused with a hybrid, &lt;i&gt;G. x billingtonii&lt;/i&gt;, which is a cross between &lt;i&gt;G. puberulenta&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;G. andrewsii&lt;/i&gt;. The hybrid however, tends to have leaves and sepal tips that are widest near the base where as in &lt;i&gt;G. saponaria&lt;/i&gt;, they are widest near the middle.  Also, the leaves of the hybrid tend to be stiffer and lighter green in color than the dark green leaves of &lt;i&gt;G. saponaria&lt;/i&gt;.  Finally, the flowers of the hybrid appear to be a deeper color blue. The species and two subspecies of &lt;i&gt;G. andrewsii&lt;/i&gt; may also be confused with &lt;i&gt;G. saponaria&lt;/i&gt;, but their leaves are much wider and possess long pointy tips.  Also, unlike &lt;i&gt;G. saponaria&lt;/i&gt; the sepal tips of &lt;i&gt;G. andrewsii&lt;/i&gt; are much shorter than the connected tube portion.</comments><nameCds><simNmCd>GEBI5</simNmCd><simNmCd>GEAN</simNmCd><simNmCd>GEANA</simNmCd><simNmCd>GEAND</simNmCd><simNmCd/><simNmCd/></nameCds><links><link><linkUri>http://plants.usda.gov/cgi_bin/plant_profile.cgi?symbol=GECA10</linkUri><linkText>Gentiana catesbaei</linkText></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></similarSpecies><flowering>September to mid-November</flowering><habitatEcology>Sandy moist prairies and Black Oak savannas, moist or seasonally wet thickets, open woods, or even along railroad tracks, but overall rare in our area.</habitatEcology><nativity>native</nativity><notes><comments>This species is now extirpated (extinct) in Michigan.  The species has a relatively wide distribution in the United States and a lot of physical variation occurs between different populations as well as within single populations (Pringle 1967).</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></notes><etymology><comments>&lt;i&gt;Gentiana&lt;/i&gt; is named after Gentius, king of Illyria, who supposedly discovered a medicinal value for the yellow gentian. &lt;i&gt;Saponaria&lt;/i&gt; refers to the resemblance of the leaves to the common soapwort, which is in the genus &lt;i&gt;Saponaria&lt;/i&gt;.</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></etymology><furtherInfo><comments/><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></furtherInfo><references><reference><citation>Pringle, J. S. 1967. Taxonomy of &lt;i&gt;Gentiana,&lt;/i&gt; section &lt;i&gt;Pneumonanthae&lt;/i&gt;, in eastern North America. Brittonia. 19:1-32.</citation></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference></references><otherRecords><ilBn>has other records</ilBn><ilCk>has other records</ilCk><ilDk/><ilDp>has other records</ilDp><ilGd/><ilKd/><ilKk/><ilKn>has other records</ilKn><ilLk>has other records</ilLk><ilMh/><ilWl>has other records</ilWl><inJs>has other records</inJs><inLk>has other records</inLk><inLp>has other records</inLp><inNt>has other records</inNt><inPt>has other records</inPt><inSj>has other records</inSj><inSk>has other records</inSk><miBr>has other records</miBr><wiKs/><wiMw/><wiRc/><wiWk/><wiWw/></otherRecords></speciesPage>