<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speciesPage><NAME_CD>FRAM2</NAME_CD><group>PLANT</group><desc><growthForm>Large tree,</growthForm><size>Large tree, 18 - 30 m high, trunk diameter 0.6 - 1.2 m. Trunk straight, extending well into the crown. Crown pyramidal or egg-shaped, with thin branches.</size><parts><part><partName>Bark</partName><partText>light to dark gray, thick, deeply furrowed with flat-topped, sometimes scaly, interwoven ridges that create a diamond-shaped pattern.</partText></part><part><partName>Twigs</partName><partText>thin, stout, dark green, mostly hairless, becoming gray or light brown. All but the current year’s epidermis appears flaky, scaly, or peeling. Leaf scars are raised (giving the twigs a knobby appearance) with several bundle scars forming a U.</partText></part><part><partName>Buds</partName><partText>dark brown, small, rounded, finely hairy. Terminal bud 5 - 14 mm long, blunt. Uppermost pair of lateral buds adjacent to terminal bud at nearly the same level.</partText></part><part><partName>Leaves</partName><partText>opposite, pinnately compound, 20 - 38 cm long, with 5 - 9 leaflets. Leaflets short-stalked, green and smooth above, paler or whitish and sometimes hairy below, 7 - 13 cm long, 2.5 - 5 cm wide, egg-shaped to oblong lance-shaped, rounded or tapering at the base, pointed at the tip, margins shallowly toothed, thick, firm. Leaves turn yellow to purple in autumn.</partText></part><part><partName>Flowers</partName><partText>either male or female, found on separate trees (dioecious); borne in a loose, branched inflorescence; purplish, tiny, without petals; calyx bell-shaped.</partText></part><part><partName>Fruit</partName><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText>dry, single-seeded, winged (samara); in crowded, branched clusters; 2.5 - 5 cm long, narrow-cylindrical; wing enclosing the tip of seed cavity, but not extending to the base. Seed cavity relatively large compared with other &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus&lt;/i&gt; species.</partText></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part></parts></desc><similarSpecies><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus americana&lt;/i&gt; is best identified by having short-stalked leaflets with pale or whitish undersides, twigs with raised leaf scars (giving them a knobby appearance), fruit with large seed cavities having a wing which doesn’t extend to the base, and a flaky, scaly, or peeling twig epidermis (except current year’s growth). &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus nigra&lt;/i&gt; has unstalked leaflets, and fruit with a wing extending near the base of the seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt; may have densely hairy shoots, and those without hairy shoots will not exhibit flaking or peeling of the epidermis. Also, the wing of its fruit encloses half or more of the seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus profunda&lt;/i&gt; has conspicuously stalked leaflets, densely hairy shoots (current), and fruit with a wing often extending to the base of the seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus quadrangulata&lt;/i&gt; has square twigs, and fruit with a wing extending to and around the base of the seed cavity.</comments><nameCds><simNmCd>FRNI</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRPE</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRPR</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRQU</simNmCd><simNmCd/><simNmCd/></nameCds><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></similarSpecies><flowering>April to mid-May, before the leaves.</flowering><habitatEcology>Dry to moist woods, valleys, and slopes.</habitatEcology><nativity>native</nativity><notes><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus americana&lt;/i&gt; is one of the more common forest trees in the Chicago Region. Its durable wood is used for many things, such as furniture, baseball bats, tennis rackets, oars, interior trim, and tool handles. The emerald ash borer (&lt;i&gt;Agrilus planipennis&lt;/i&gt;) is a serious insect threat to all native ashes (see link below).</comments><links><link><linkUri>Emerald Ash Borer</linkUri><linkText>http://www.emeraldashborer.info/</linkText></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></notes><etymology><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus&lt;/i&gt; is the Latin word for the Ash tree. &lt;i&gt;Americana&lt;/i&gt; means “from America.”</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></etymology><furtherInfo><comments/><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></furtherInfo><references><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference></references><otherRecords><ilBn/><ilCk>has other records</ilCk><ilDk>has other records</ilDk><ilDp>has other records</ilDp><ilGd>has other records</ilGd><ilKd>has other records</ilKd><ilKk/><ilKn>has other records</ilKn><ilLk>has other records</ilLk><ilMh>has other records</ilMh><ilWl>has other records</ilWl><inJs>has other records</inJs><inLk>has other records</inLk><inLp>has other records</inLp><inNt>has other records</inNt><inPt>has other records</inPt><inSj>has other records</inSj><inSk>has other records</inSk><miBr>has other records</miBr><wiKs/><wiMw>has other records</wiMw><wiRc>has other records</wiRc><wiWk/><wiWw>has other records</wiWw></otherRecords></speciesPage>