<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speciesPage><NAME_CD>FRNI</NAME_CD><group>PLANT</group><desc><growthForm>DUMMYDATA</growthForm><size>Medium-sized tree, 12 - 20 m tall, trunk diameter 30 cm - 0.6 m. Trunk often leaning or crooked, extending to the top of the crown. Crown narrow, rounded, with many stout, straight branches.</size><parts><part><partName>Bark</partName><partText>ashy gray, thin, fissured into soft, scaly plates that may flake off when rubbed.</partText></part><part><partName>Twigs</partName><partText>stout, dark green, smooth, becoming light gray then dark gray and warty. Leaf scars oval, with several bundle scars forming a U.</partText></part><part><partName>Buds</partName><partText>bluish black, small, conical, finely hairy. Terminal bud 4 - 10 mm long, pointed. Uppermost pair of lateral buds up to 1 cm below the base of terminal bud.</partText></part><part><partName>Leaves</partName><partText>opposite, pinnately compound, 25 - 40 cm long, with 7 - 11 leaflets. Leaflets stalkless (except for the terminal), dark green and smooth above, paler with rusty hairs along the veins beneath, 7 - 15 cm long, 2.5 - 5 cm wide, oblong to oblong lance-shaped, tapering or rounded at the base, long-pointed at the tip, margins toothed, thin, firm. Leaves turn reddish brown in autumn.</partText></part><part><partName>Flowers</partName><partText>either male, female, or bisexual; usually found on separate trees, but sometimes on the same tree (polygamodioecious); borne in an elongated, branched inflorescence; purplish, small, without petals.</partText></part><part><partName>Fruit</partName><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText>dry, single-seeded, winged (samara); in open, branched clusters; 2.5 - 4.5 cm long, oblong, barely notched at the tip; wing broad, often twisted, extending near the base of the flat seed cavity.</partText></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part></parts></desc><similarSpecies><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus nigra&lt;/i&gt; is best identified by having unstalked leaflets, thin, ashy gray bark fissured into soft, scaly plates, and fruit with a broad, often twisted wing extending near the base of the flat seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus americana&lt;/i&gt; has short-stalked leaflets with pale or whitish undersides, twigs with raised leaf scars, fruit with large seed cavities having a wing which doesn’t extend to the base, and a flaky, scaly, or peeling twig epidermis (except current year’s growth). &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus pennsylvanica&lt;/i&gt; may have densely hairy shoots, and the wing of its fruit encloses half or more of the seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus profunda&lt;/i&gt; has conspicuously stalked leaflets, densely hairy shoots (current), and fruit with a wing often extending to the base of the seed cavity. &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus quadrangulata&lt;/i&gt; has square twigs, and fruit with a wing extending to and around the base of the seed cavity.</comments><nameCds><simNmCd>FRAM2</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRPE</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRPR</simNmCd><simNmCd>FRQU</simNmCd><simNmCd/><simNmCd/></nameCds><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></similarSpecies><flowering>Late April, before the leaves.</flowering><habitatEcology>Local in moist woods, swamps, fens, floodplains, and other mesic sites. However, its most characteristic habitat is on calcareous springy slopes.</habitatEcology><nativity>native</nativity><notes><comments>The wood of &lt;i&gt;Fraxinus nigra&lt;/i&gt; is used for baskets, barrel hoops, woven chair bottoms, fence posts, cabinets, interior finish, and furniture. The emerald ash borer (&lt;i&gt;Agrilus planipennis&lt;/i&gt;) is a serious insect threat to all native ashes (see link below).</comments><links><link><linkUri>Emerald Ash Borer</linkUri><linkText>http://www.emeraldashborer.info/</linkText></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></notes><etymology><comments>&lt;i&gt;Fraxinus&lt;/i&gt; is the Latin word for ash. &lt;i&gt;Nigra&lt;/i&gt; is Latin for black, referring to its dark brown heartwood.</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></etymology><furtherInfo><comments/><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></furtherInfo><references><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference></references><otherRecords><ilBn>has other records</ilBn><ilCk>has other records</ilCk><ilDk>has other records</ilDk><ilDp>has other records</ilDp><ilGd>has other records</ilGd><ilKd>has other records</ilKd><ilKk/><ilKn>has other records</ilKn><ilLk>has other records</ilLk><ilMh>has other records</ilMh><ilWl>has other records</ilWl><inJs/><inLk>has other records</inLk><inLp>has other records</inLp><inNt/><inPt>has other records</inPt><inSj/><inSk>has other records</inSk><miBr>has other records</miBr><wiKs/><wiMw>has other records</wiMw><wiRc>has other records</wiRc><wiWk/><wiWw>has other records</wiWw></otherRecords></speciesPage>