<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<speciesPage><NAME_CD>TSCA</NAME_CD><group>PLANT</group><desc><growthForm>DUMMYDATA</growthForm><size>Tree, 22 - 30 m tall, trunk diameter 0.5 - 1.5 m. Pyramidal, dense crown with drooping topmost shoot; lower branches often drooping down to the ground. A rounded top is typically found on large, mature trees.</size><parts><part><partName>Bark</partName><partText>reddish brown, thick, deeply furrowed into wide, scaly ridges. Inner bark reddish purple, observed when broken or cut.</partText></part><part><partName>Twigs</partName><partText>slender; pale brown and hairy when young, becoming grayish brown and smooth with age.</partText></part><part><partName>Buds</partName><partText>reddish brown, 1.5 - 2 mm long, egg-shaped.</partText></part><part><partName>Needles</partName><partText>on short, thin stalks; shiny green above with 2 whitish bands below, 0.6 - 1.4 cm long, 1 - 2 mm wide, linear, flat, flexible, apex rounded, margins minutely toothed near apex, spirally arranged around the shoot, appearing 2-ranked by the twisting of the needle stalks.</partText></part><part><partName>Pollen cones</partName><partText>yellowish, about 1 cm long, spherical, near the ends of branchlets.</partText></part><part><partName>Young seed cones</partName><partText>Mature seed cones</partText></part><part><partName>woody, short-stalked, hanging down at ends of twigs, reddish to light brown, 1.3 - 2 cm long, cylindrical to egg-shaped; scales thin with rounded, smooth (or faintly toothed) margins. Seeds light brown, 1 - 3 mm long, triangular, with wings twice as long.</partName><partText>pale green, about 3 mm long, cylindrical, near the ends of branchlets. Pollination between cones occurs in spring.</partText></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part><part><partName/><partText/></part></parts></desc><similarSpecies><comments>&lt;i&gt;Tsuga canadensis&lt;/i&gt; can be distinguished from other trees in the Pine family by its short, flat needles appearing 2-ranked, its reddish purple inner bark, its small seed cones with smooth scale margins, its foliage flattened in a single plane, and its drooping leader shoot. There are no hemlocks native to the Chicago Region.</comments><nameCds><simNmCd/><simNmCd/><simNmCd/><simNmCd/><simNmCd/><simNmCd/></nameCds><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></similarSpecies><flowering/><habitatEcology>In the Chicago Region, &lt;i&gt;Tsuga canadensis&lt;/i&gt; is only known to occur in Berrien County, Michigan, where it is frequent in old dune slopes. It also occurs in swampy woodlands. Outside the region it grows in cool, moist valleys or ravines, and is fond of rocky ridges and slopes. However, &lt;i&gt;T. canadensis&lt;/i&gt; will grow in a variety of sites and soils. Seedlings are often found growing on rotting logs and moss covered rocks. &lt;i&gt;T. canadensis&lt;/i&gt; is a shade-tolerant tree that can live 600 years or more. It grows slowly, existing for 50 - 100 years in the shaded understory until finally reaching the overstory. Over time, the litter from its fallen twigs and needles causes acidic soil conditions. This, combined with the tree’s shade and absorption of moisture, discourages most plants from growing beneath it.</habitatEcology><nativity>native</nativity><notes><comments>Numerous cultivars have been developed from &lt;i&gt;T. canadensis&lt;/i&gt;, including shrubs, dwarfs, and graceful trees. The wood is not very durable, but is used for pulp, general construction, boxes, crates, sashes, doors, and cabinets. It is not recommended for firewood because of its tendency to pop, shooting sparks for several feet. The bark was once the main source of natural tannin for leather.</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></notes><etymology><comments>&lt;i&gt;Tsuga&lt;/i&gt; is the Japanese word for the hemlock tree. &lt;i&gt;Canadensis&lt;/i&gt; refers to Canada, but is also used in reference to North America—a result of early French influence.</comments><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></etymology><furtherInfo><comments/><links><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></links></furtherInfo><references><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><citation/></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference><reference><link><linkUri/><linkText/></link></reference></references><otherRecords><ilBn/><ilCk/><ilDk/><ilDp/><ilGd/><ilKd/><ilKk/><ilKn/><ilLk/><ilMh/><ilWl/><inJs/><inLk/><inLp/><inNt/><inPt/><inSj/><inSk/><miBr>has other records</miBr><wiKs/><wiMw/><wiRc/><wiWk/><wiWw>has other records</wiWw></otherRecords></speciesPage>