<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<speciesPage> 
<NAME_CD>AGARCAMP2</NAME_CD> 
<group>FUNGUS</group> 

<desc> <growthForm>Gilled mushroom</growthForm> 
<size>cap 3 - 11 cm broad; stem 2 - 6 cm long, 10 - 25 mm thick.</size> 
<parts> 
<part> <partName>Cap</partName> <partText>convex to broadly convex, sometimes becoming flat with age,  white to pale gray.  Surface smooth, dry, sometimes covered with fine brownish-gray fibers or scales in dry conditions.  Flesh thick, white, unchanging when bruised or cut, may stain reddish-brown with age, not staining yellow with KOH.</partText> </part> 
<part> <partName>Gills</partName> <partText>free, crowded to close, narrow, pink when young eventually becoming blackish-brown.</partText> </part> 
<part> <partName>Partial veil</partName> <partText>may leave remnants on cap margin and forms a thin, membranous, quickly collapsing ring on the middle to upper part of stem that typically disappears with age. </partText> </part> 
<part> <partName>Stem</partName> <partText>stout,  tapering to a pointed base, white, turning reddish-brown, smooth above ring, covered with fine fibers or hairs below; stuffed to hollow. </partText> </part> 
<part> <partName>Odor</partName> <partText>mild.</partText> </part> 
<part> <partName>Taste</partName> <partText>slightly of anise.</partText> </part> 
<part> <partName>Spore print</partName> <partText>blackish-brown. </partText> </part> 
<part> <partName>Microscopic features</partName> <partText>spores 6 - 8.5 x 4 - 5.5 &amp;micro;m, elliptical, smooth.</partText> </part> 
</parts> 
</desc> 

<similarSpecies> 
<comments>The most common, but not the only &lt;em&gt;Agaricus&lt;/em&gt; species in lawns.  &lt;em&gt;Agaricus bitorquis&lt;/em&gt; has thicker flesh, a double ring, and doesn't have the bright pink gills when young.  Other species have scaly or differently colored caps, or yellow staining, or stronger odors. </comments> 
<nameCds> 
<simNmCd>AGARBITO</simNmCd> 
<simNmCd>AGARPLAC</simNmCd> 
<simNmCd>AGARXANT2</simNmCd> 
</nameCds> 
<links> 
<link> <linkUri>http://www.bluewillowpages.com/mushroomexpert/agaricus_xanthodermus.html</linkUri> <linkText>Agaricus xanthodermus</linkText> </link> 
</links> 
</similarSpecies> 

<fruiting>July to November.</fruiting> 

<habitatEcology>Common in lawns and grassy areas. Solitary to gregarious, sometimes in fairy rings, on soil. Soil saprobe that prefers lawns.</habitatEcology> 

<notes> 
<comments>Was also called "common mushroom, champignon, or hot-bed mushroom" when it was thought to be the same species as the common store mushroom &lt;i&gt;Agaricus bisporus&lt;/i&gt;, which is from the eastern Mediterranean.  This and other urban mushrooms can accumulate chemicals, toxins, and heavy metals from the surrounding soil. </comments> 
<links>
<link>
<linkUri/> 
<linkText/>  
</link> 
</links>
</notes> 

<etymology> <comments>&lt;em&gt;Agaricon&lt;/em&gt; is an ancient Greek word for particular fungi, reportedly derived from Agara, the name of a Greek city which had abundant mushrooms nearby.  &lt;em&gt;Campestris&lt;/em&gt; is derived from the same word as campus, meaning a field.  </comments> 
<links> 
<link>
<linkUri/> 
<linkText/> 
</link>  
</links>
</etymology> 

<furtherInfo>
<comments/> 
<links> <link> <linkUri>http://www.bluewillowpages.com/mushroomexpert/agaricus_campestris.html</linkUri> <linkText>Michael Kuo, E. Ill. Univ., MushroomExpert.com</linkText> </link> </links> </furtherInfo> 

<references> <reference> <citation/> </reference> </references> 

<otherRecords> <ilBn/> <ilCk/> <ilDk/> <ilDp/> <ilGd/> <ilKd/> <ilKk/> <ilKn/> <ilLk/> <ilMh/> <ilWl/> <inJs/> <inLk/> <inLp/> <inNt/> <inPt/> <inSj/> <inSk/> <miBr/> <wiKs/> <wiMw/> <wiRc/> <wiWk/> <wiWw/> </otherRecords> 

<author>The Field Museum</author> 
<modificationDate>2006-05-29</modificationDate> 
</speciesPage> 